Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  - National Edge City Philadelphia, August 1987-May 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Documents about Philadelphia. Material includes "At the Crossroads: The Consequences of Economic Stability or Decline in Philadelphia for the City, Region and Commonwealth" by Theodore Hershberg, an article about King of Prussia, Regional Mobility Policy Analysis from the Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission, a letter to Garreau from James Timberlake, Philadelphia Inquirer articles about zoning and suburban homes, a packet of maps, an issue of Welcomat, a Philadelphia Magazine article "Off the Cuff" by D. Herbert Lipson, notes, an article from Progressive Architecture about the suburbs and a Washington Post article about Philadelphia.
  - National Edge City Foundry Philadelphia, May 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    A Washington Post article about Philadelphia.
  - National Edge City Philly King of Prussia, May 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Notes about Philadelphia and King of Prussia including contact information for Scott Sibley.
  - Local Edge City Anne Arundel, October 1985-July 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Two copies of A Comprehensive Growth Management Program for Anne Arundel County also included is a letter to Garreau from Robert D. Agee.
  - Local Edge City Urban Land Institute Bethesda, January-November 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Documents and correspondence about the Urban Land Institute and Bethesda, MD. Material includes notes, "Economic Evaluation Bethesda Suburban Activity Center" by Sandra P. Smith, "Urban Land Institute Suburban Activity Centers Study: Bethesda, Maryland Central Business District Physical Design Aspects" by Sherwin Greene, Downtown Bethesda Commercial Inventory, Bethesda Retail Stores, two copies of a questionnaire for Urban Land Institute's Bethesda Project, a map of a self guided walking tour or Bethesda, an article from the Montgomery County Sentinel, an pamphlet describing the updates of Rivkin Associates, a calendar of events in Bethesda for November and December of 1987, a pamphlet for Bethesda-Chevy Chase Center, "Downtown Bethesda Social Roles and Functions", a Bethesda shopping guide, Capital Crescent Parkland pamphlet, "The Future Doesn't Work" by Douglas R. Porter and a note to Garreau about the article, "Criteria for Judging the Quality of the Urban Environment" by Hans Blumenfeld and two articles from the Bethesda Business Review "A Moving Experience" by Lee Rubner and "How Will Bethesda's Boom Effect The Small Retailer?" by Carole McCord.
  - Local Edge City Centreville, November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    A Washington Post article about the growth of Centreville, VA retail.
  - Local Edge City Charles County, July 1987-November 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Documents about Charles County, MD including a press release and a Washington Post article about growth in Charles County.
  - Local Edge City Chrystal City, October 1987-July 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Two articles about development in Chrystal City. A Washington Business article about real estate developers and a Washington Post article about the shopping mall in Pentagon City.
  - Local Edge City Columbia, August 1976, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Material about Columbia, MD, including a brochure "The People of Columbia", an article from The Columbia Flier about a Marriott theme park and a "Newcomers Guide" to Columbia.
  - Local Edge City DC Ward 2 (Downtown), April 1987-August 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Documents about Ward 2 in Washington, DC. Material includes a Washington, DC Real Estate Market Report and a Washington Post article.
  - Local Edge City Dulles CIT, August 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    An article about the Center for Innovative Technology in Herndon, VA.
  - Local Edge City Dulles, June 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    A Washington Post article about a United Airlines reservations center near Dulles international airport.
  - Local Edge City Dulles Toll Rd, February-June 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Two articles about the Dulles Toll Road. Washington Post articles "The Man Behind the Dulles Toll Road Plan" by Steve Bates and "Putting Executives in the Lap of Luxury" by Nan Powers.
  - Local Edge City Dulles Rt 28 Corridor Mobil, February-October 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Two Washington Post articles "Mobil Subsidiary to Develop Large Land Tract in Loudoun" by Cornelius F. Foote, Jr. and "Riggs to Foreclose on 4 Dulles Corridor Office Buildings" by David S. Hilzenrath.
  - Local Edge City Education, April 1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    A Washington Post pamphlet about Washington, DC education.
  - Local Edge City Fairfax Center 1 of 2, May 1985-August 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Documents about Fairfax County government land development. Material includes a Washington Business article "Fairfax Weighs Joint Venture" by Marcia McAllister, a Washington Post article "Booming Fair Oaks Eyes Future Warily" by Tom Precious and a notebook "Fair Oaks Clayton Wine".
  - Local Edge City Fairfax Center 2 of 2, November 1985-January 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Documents about Fairfax County government land development. Material includes the November 1985 issue of Virginia Business, a January 1990 supplement to Virginia Business about Fairfax and "Subdivision Recycling: What Happens When Metro Moves in Next Door There Goes the Neighborhood No One Wants to Get Their Kicks Living Right on Route 66" with an introduction to the paper.
  - Local Edge City Frederick, July-January 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Documents about Frederick County. Material includes a booklet of demographic and development data, a Washington Post article about Frederick becoming more urban, notes, a press release and a Rockville Gazette article about model homes.
  - Local Edge City Gainesville Prince William County, March-November 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Documents about Prince William County. Material includes the Winter 1989 issue of the Prince William Report, a Fauquier Democrat article "Stonecrest is flexed to be 'interceptor'" by Irena Von Zahn, a news paper section about development in Manassas and an issue of Manassas Weekly Gazette.
  - Local Edge City Proposed Howard County, February 1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    A Washington Post article about development in Howard County.
  - Local Edge City I-95, December 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    A Baltimore Sun article about the corridor of Interstate 95 between Baltimore and Washington.
  - Local Edge City Loudoun County, November 1988-October 1989 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Three Washington Post articles "Woman's Love for Home Exceeds $1.9 Million" by DeNeen L. Brown, "Loudoun Envisions Urban-Rural Balance" by Cornelius F. Foote Jr. and "Office Space in Loudoun 40% Vacant" by Cornelius F. Foote Jr.
  - Local Edge City Leesburg Cascades, October 1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Documents about the planned community Cascades in Leesburg, VA. Material includes two newspaper advertisements for the Cascades, a Cascade promotional publication and a contact list of builders.
  - Local Edge City Loudoun County, December 1986-June 1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Documents about Loudoun County, VA. Material includes an article from the Loudoun Times Mirror about a mall, a Washington Post article about a housing project in Loudoun county, a map of the Xerox facility and the June 1987 issue of Loudoun area real estate guide.
  - Local Edge City Merrifield Mobil 1 of 3, April 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Documents about Mobil Oil Company and J.C. Penney. Material includes a New York Times article "J.C. Penney Plans Move to Dallas From New York, Consultants Say" by Albert Scardino, notes, Mobil Annual Report 1986, a Washington Post article by Joel Garreau about a forest owned by Mobil, a number of microfilm printouts about mobil, a biography of Allen E. Murray head of Mobil and other article printouts.
  - Local Edge City Merrifield Mobil 2 of 3, September 1976-August 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Documents and correspondence about Mobil Oil Company. Material includes an article about Mobil consolidating from New York to Fairfax, a Mobil employee announcement, "Economic Impact of Mobil's Proposed Headquarters Office on the County of Fairfax", a comparative analysis of projected and actual Fairfax County tax revenues generated by the Mobil Oil Corporate headquarters and other article printouts.
  - Local Edge Cuty Merrifield Mobil 3 of 3, May 1987-September 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Documents and correspondence about the Mobil Oil Company's move to Fairfax, VA. Material includes notes, Washington Post articles "Mobil Makes Its Move" by B.H. Lawrence and "Yes, Virginia, There Is a Mobil Corp." and "Mobil's Move to Fairfax May Spark a Trend" by Joel Garreau, promotional publications for Fairview Park a planned corporate community in Fairfax County, VA, four copies of an anonymous letter to Garreau in response to his Post article "Mobil's Move to Fairfax..."and transcripts of Garreau articles.
  - Local Edge City Montgomery County 1 of 3, August 1985-September 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Documents about Montgomery County, MD. Material includes Washington Post articles "Kramer Runs as Practitioner of Consensus Politics" by R.H. Melton, "Kramer's Plans Could Shape County - or Divide It" by Molly Sinclair, a collection of articles about Northern Virginia county elections, a Washington Flyer magazine article "Silver Spring on the Rebound" by Ellen Klein, notes, a Washington Post insert about the National Institutes of Health and transcripts of Washington Post articles "Suburban Diary" by Arthur S. Brisbane, "Bethesda Business District Gets a Boost" by Joan McQueeney Mitric and "Montgomery Unveils Capital Budget, Growth Policy" by Gwen Ifill and "Court Says Building is Too Big; Maryland Appeals Panel Orders Reduction in Size of Silver Spring Structure" by Beth Schwinn.
  - Local Edge City Montgomery County 2 of 3, June 1988-August 1989 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Documents about Montgomery County, MD. Material includes "Envisioning Our Future" a Report on The Commission on The Future of Montgomery County, Maryland, a business card from Bruce Adams and Washington Post articles "An Upbeat Upcounty Reshapes Montgomery" by Sue Anne Pressley, "Montgomery Survey Finds Unconcern on Drugs" by Paul Duggan, "Setbacks Dull the Luster of Silver Triangle Project in Montgomery" by Jo-Ann Armao and "Prayers and Gin for F. Scott Fitzgerald" by Jim Naughton
  - Local Edge City Montgomery County 3 of 3, June 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Documents about Montgomery County, MD. Material includes a Washington Post article "The Question of Housing" by Benjamin Forgey, a folder of status reports of projects from the Montgomery County Department of Transportation, "Transportation (Not Traffic) Management in a Rapidly Urbanizing Area" a report from the director of the Montgomery County Department of Transportation, Robert S. McGarry, notes and the second printing of "Envisioning Our Future" a Report on The Commission on The Future of Montgomery County, Maryland.
  - Local Edge City Middleburg 1 of 4, December 1986-April 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Documents about Middleburg, VA. Material includes notes, a transcript of a Joel Garreau article from the Washington Post, a collection of article transcripts about Middleburg, Va, a collection of article transcripts about Round Hill, VA, a transcript of a Washington Post article "Expanding An Empire in Real Estate; Developers of Crystal City Plan to Double Holdings" by Malcolm Gladwell, "A Walk With History" a booklet published for the Middleburg Bicentennial and the October 1987 and March 1988 issues of Middleburg Life.
  - Local Edge City Middleburg 2 of 4, February-April 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Documents about Middleburg, VA. Material includes notes, a pamphlet about open space easements, two notebooks, an advertisement for businesses and restaurants in Middleburg, a transcript of a Joel Garreau article, Robert T. Dennis's business card for Piedmont Environmental Council, a brochure for a fine art auction, the February 1988 Piedmont Environment Council newsletter and a promotional publication for Newstead Farm.
  - Local Edge City Middleburg 3 of 4, April-July 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Documents about Middleburg, VA. Material includes two copies of a Washington Post article about Middleburg by Joel Garreau, demographics of Middleburg, a menu for Mosbys a Middleburg restaurant, volume 108 of Estates The International Magazine for Luxury Estates and note transcripts.
  - Local Edge City Middleburg 4 of 4, October 1986-May 1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Documents about Middleburg, VA. Material includes the Piedmont Environmental Council 1987 annual report, notes, pamphlets about open space easements, Virginia's Agricultural and Forestal District Act, Virginia Piedmont Reserve Needed Today - For Tomorrow, The Red Fox Tavern and Voluntary Landscape Conservation, a transcript of a Joel Garreau article, an advertisement for the Red Fox Inn, note transcripts, a notice for a fine art auction in Middleburg, a map of Middleburg and selections from the books "Jefferson and the Ordeal of Liberty" by Dumas Malone, "Legends of Loudoun" by Harrison Williams, "Virginia The New Dominion" by Virginius Dabney and an article "Loudoun Heritage".
  - National Edge City San Diego, June 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Documents about San Diego, CA. Material includes a brochure for a group of museums called Balboa Park and an "Analysis of Redevelopment Opportunities for the San Diego State University Campus Study Area in San Diego, California".
  - National Edge City San Jose/Silicon Valley Market Reports, January 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    A Real Estate market report for San Jose and Silicon Valley research and development and office markets.
  - The Edge City Group, January 1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Documents about Cobb County, GA including a letter from Tad Leithead to Joel Garreau about the development of Cobb County and a promotional publication for economic progress in Cobb County.
  - National Edge City Houston Market Report, June 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Documents about development in Houston, TX including two copies of the Houston Real Estate Market report and "Outlook 92 The Commercial Real Estate Market".
  - National Edge City Milwaukee Blue Mound, June 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    An article from the Milwaukee Journal "The future is here" by Jill Zuckman.
  - Edge Ecology Civilizations, October 1982-November 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Documents about the effects of development on ecology. Material includes "Avian Nest Dispersion and Fledging Success in Field-Forest Ecotones" by J. Edward Gates and Leslie W. Gysel, J. Edwards Gates's University of Maryland business card, "Habitat Use By The Southern Flying Squirrel At A Hemlock-Northern Hardwood Ecotone" by Robert M. Gilmore and J. Edward Gates, "The Self-Reproducing Universe" by Eugene F. Mallove, the October 1982 issue of Wildlife Monographs, "Use Of Forest Edge and Strip Vegetation By Eastern Cottontails" by Kevin A. Morgan and J. Edward Gates, "Effects of Interstate Highway Fencing on White-Tailed Deer Activity" by George A. Feldhamer, J. Edward Gates, Dan M. Harman, Andre J. Loranger and Kenneth R Dixon and "Bird Population Patterns in Forest Edge and Strip Vegetation at Remington Farms, Maryland" by Kevin A. Morgan and J. Edward Gates.
  - Landscape Ugliness of Edge Cities, 1982-September 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Documents about the effects of Edge Cites on the landscape. Material includes an article from Landscape Magazine "Facing Up to Ambiguity" by Peirce Lewis, notes, a newspaper article about developers in Historic Waterford, VA, a transcript of an article by Peirce Lewis, Washington Post articles "Hatcheries: The Buffers Between Rock, Hard Place" by Angus Phillips and "Back To Eden: Images From The Landscape of The Imagined" by Henry Allen, a magazine article "Personal History Impalpable Dust" by M.R. Montgomery, a letter to Garreau from Susan Sharpe about an essay on landscape, Newsweek articles "Are Cities Obsolete?" by Tom Morganthau and John McCormick and "Reversal of Fortune" by Bill Turque and a booklet "Axioms For Reading the Landscape" by Peirce Lewis. Also included are a number of book reviews of "Borderland: Origins of The American Suburb" by John R. Stilgoe, "William Wordsworth: A Life" by Stephen Gill, "Great Plains" by Ian Frazier, "Placeways: A Theory of the Human Environment" by Eugene Victor Walter, "The Architect of Exile" by Stanley Tigerman and "Idea of a Town: The Anthropology of Urban Form in Rome, Italy and the Ancient World" by Joseph Rykwert. Theory
  - National Edge City California Central Valley, February 1989-April 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Two newspaper articles. A Wall Street Journal article "In California Valley, Costs Too Are Low" by William Celis and a USA Today article "California looks at splitting up" by Maria Goodavage.
  - National Edge City Los Angeles, July 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    A Wall Street Journal article "Giving LA's Future Balanced Look Today" by Roger Selbert.
  - National Edge City Boston James Vance Interview, October 1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Notes and a transcription of an interview with James Vance.
  - National Edge City Magazine Articles, June 1987-February 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Magazine articles about edge cities. Articles include "Serv-Urbs, USA" by Steven R. Malin and two Time magazine articles "Spiffing Up The Urban Heritage" by Kurt Anderson and "The Boom Towns" by George J Church.
  - National Edge City Boston Walden Pond, September 1981-April 1990 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    Documents about Walden Pond area outside Boston, MA. Material includes a pamphlet for Walden Pond State Reservation, Washington Post articles "Plans for Developing Walden Raise Star=Studded Opposition" by Christopher B Daly and Crowds, "Commerce and Conflict at Thoreau's Walden" by Michael Rezendes and "Reflections: Why, It's the Sky!" by K.C. Cole, a Newsweek article "Battling Over Walden Woods" by Mark Starr, notes, a transcript of a Washington Post article "Crowds, Commerce, and Conflict at Thoreau's Walden" by Michael Rezendes, Providence Journal-Bulletin articles "Thoreau followers battle project" and "Developers turn hungry eye to Walden Pond", an article from the Environmentalist "Education for Life in the Sky" by Charles E. Roth, an article from the Amicus Journal "For Spacious Skies" by Joanna J Berkman, a New York Times article "Seeing the Sky: Not a Limit but Infinity" by Matthew L Wald, a letter from Ansel Adams to Russell E Dickenson, the director of the National Park Service, an article "The Modern World Encroaches, but Walden Pond Lives On" by Nicholas King and a Time magazine article "When the Sky's the Limit" by Joelle Attinger.
  - The Edge City News, April 1993-February 1996 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Twenty four editions of The Edge City News. A publication informing the reader about "what is happening around the frontier" covering "developments-in-progress, events, conferences, books, RFP's (request for proposals), people and places in the news, and changes in the law-gleanings from our sources across the country". The folder contains editions ranging from the first edition, Volume 1, number 1 to Volume 3, number 4. Also included is a hand-written letter from a "Wilson" to "Dr. Koda" on The Edge City Group stationary about printed material and pictures.
  - Washington Post Business Section 1 of 2, April 1989 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Two copies of the 3 April 1989 business section featuring an article by Kristin Downey "Emerging Cities: The Boom Goes On".
  - Washington Post Business Section 2 of 2, April 1989 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    The 17 April 1989 Business Section of the Washington Post featuring an article about the Washington area's largest public companies.
  - Governing the States and Localities Penelope Lemov, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Penelope Lemov's Governing The States and Localities business card.
  - Economics of Development Use Value Taxation, December 1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    A Washington Post article by Brooke A. Masters, "Cash Slips Through Loophole".
  - Economics of Development International, September 1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    A Washington Post article by Jerry DeMuth, "Developers Look Overseas for Growth".
  - No Growth Transcript, July 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Two transcripts of an discussion about the politics of low growth.
  - Economic Development Baerwald, May-June 1989 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    "Changing Sales Pattern in Major American Metropolises, 1963-1982" by Thomas J. Baerwald.
  - Economics of Development Local Land Costs, September 1988-April 1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Three Washington Post articles. "Developers Looking Beyond the Beltway" by Graeme Browning, "Last Fairfax Dairy Farmer Holds Out for Love of the Land" by Naomi S. Travers and "For New-Home Buyers, a Land-Cost Squeeze" by Ann Mariano.
  - Economics of Development New England, August 1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    An article from The Economist about economic development in New England.
  - Economics of Development National Britain, March 1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    An article from The Economist about development in Great Britain, "A green and pleasant ministry".
  - Residential Association - General, May 1989-January 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Documents about residential community associations. Material includes two publications from the Advisory Commission on Intergovernmental Relations "Residential Community Associations: Private Governments in the Intergovernmental Systems?" and "Questions and Answers for Public Officials", a memo from the Arizona State Land Development, the Desert Ridge Disposition Strategy, a Phoenix Metropolitan Area Master Planned Community Report, part of the ULI Homes Association Handbook and Douglas M. Kleine's Community Associations Institute business card.
  - Residential Association - Cornell Law Review, November 1989 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    The November 1989 issue of Cornell Law Review.
  - Residential Association - Salt River Project 1 of 2, June 1982-December 1990 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Documents about the Salt River Project. Material includes "Cities and Homeowners Associations" and "A Reply to Michelman and Frug" by Robert C. Ellickson, two booklets with information about Slat River Project Canals, A.J. Pfister's and Mike Rappaport's Salt River Project business cards, a booklet titled "Salt River Project has Bright Ideas for You", a brochure of questions and answers about the Salt River Project, the 1989-1990 Salt River Project Annual Report, notes and a map of the Salt River Project and Central Arizona.
  - Residential Association - Salt River Project 2 of 2, October-November 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Documents about the Salt River Project. Documents include a promotional publication about the Salt River Project, "A Valley Reborn The Story of the Salt River Project", Mike Rappaport's Salt River Project business card, media articles about the Jack Pfister and the Salt River Project, an "Arizona Experience" pamphlet, an Arizona Republic article "State's bridges declared in best shape in nation" by Joyce Valdez, a Phoenix Gazette article "Pfister resets SRP exit date" by Dawn Gilbertson, "Salt River Valley Trek Through Time", a promotional publication for CBS Property Services and Robert J. Burnand's CBS Property Services business card.
  - Tyson Photo [Atlanta], April 1992 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Photographs and notes about Tysons Corner and Atlanta, Georgia.
  - Tysons Corner Photos, 1935-May 1991 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    Images and notes of Tysons Corner, Virginia. Also included is a letter to Garreau from Brian A. Conley.
  - Reston, VA, Undated (Box 7, Folder 15)